A Guide to the James Burleigh Lucas Papers, 1926-1930
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
James Burleigh Lucas Papers 1926-1930
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms68-005
2 containers; 0.7 cu. ft.
Lecture and laboratory notes of James Burleigh Lucas, a professor of chemistry at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, mostly taken while Lucas attended graduate courses at the University of Illinois.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The James Burleigh Lucas Papers were donated to Newman Library prior to 1968.
Biographical Information
James Burleigh Lucas, professor of chemistry at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, was born on March 30, 1888, the son of James Crockett and Nannie Cecil Lucas. He graduated from Virginia Tech in 1910 with a degree in applied chemistry, having matriculated from Riner, Virginia. Lucas joined the faculty of Virginia Tech in 1916. Becoming an associate professor of chemistry in 1919, Lucas took graduate chemistry coursework at the University of Illinois during the 1920s. In 1948, he was named a full professor of chemistry at Virginia Tech, serving in that position until his death on October 2, 1955.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of James Burleigh Lucas, a professor of chemistry at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University ("Virginia Tech") during the first half of the twentieth century. The collection consists of eleven notebooks containing Lucas' lecture and laboratory notes, most seeming to have been maintained by Lucas while attending summer graduate courses at the University of Illinois during the 1920s. The courses in which the notes were taken include both organic and inorganic chemistry, covering basic through advanced chemistry. A single notebook from Lucas' years at Virginia Tech is labeled "alkaloids, etc." and contains just a few pages of sources and miscellaneous notes.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in chronological order. Where known, course numbers and titles are included in the item descriptions.
Contents List
- Alkaloids, etc. 1926 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Chemistry S14b - Organic chemistry 1926 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Physiological chemistry S506 1928 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Chemistry S14d - Organic chemistry laboratory [1929] (Box-folder 1-4)
- Chemistry S38a - [Qualitative organic analysis] [1929] (Box-folder 1-5)
- Chemistry S15a - [Problems of metabolism] [1930] (Box-folder 1-6)
- Chemistry S132a - Organic chemistry 1930 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Chemistry 124a - [Quantitative analysis] n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Chemistry 132c n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
- Chemistry S92 n.d. (Box-folder 2-3)
- Chemistry lab 14 n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)